Hmm.
[SPEAKER_01]: I had a couple of thoughts.
[SPEAKER_01]: One thing I thought about was heedfulness or diligence.
[SPEAKER_01]: They're translated in different ways.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, it's the quality that the Buddha says is where all skillful qualities converge and is like the way to not decline in the dhamma.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, like,
[SPEAKER_01]: What is it?
[SPEAKER_01]: And who does it apply to?
[SPEAKER_01]: Where does it start?
[SPEAKER_01]: Anybody else want to say something?
[SPEAKER_01]: Any opinions here?
[SPEAKER_03]: How it applies to sotāpanna?
[SPEAKER_03]: So, the heedfulness...
[SPEAKER_03]: So, can somebody without a right view be heedful?
[SPEAKER_01]: No.
[SPEAKER_02]: I mean, in a common sense, yes.
[SPEAKER_02]: Yeah.
[SPEAKER_02]: Whatever you want to achieve, you have to be hateful.
[SPEAKER_03]: So, it actually applies even before sotāpanna, in a sense that if you recognize that it is your task to develop the right view, and then you're hateful in regard to that task, it is the hatefulness that will make you seek the right view.
[SPEAKER_03]: And then, obviously, once you have the right view, that hatefulness will make you develop it further.
[SPEAKER_03]: So, that's why the Buddha singled it out as the as the soul factor, because he would... he would actually pertain to somebody from the moment of hearing about the possibility of freedom from suffering to the moment of understanding the freedom from suffering and then fully developing it.
[SPEAKER_03]: If he is heedful, he would... he would find a way.
[SPEAKER_01]: Will that alone make him find a way?
[SPEAKER_03]: Oh, no, of course not.
[SPEAKER_03]: No, no, no.
[SPEAKER_03]: You... that's why, yeah, you can be heedful, but...
[SPEAKER_03]: If you don't come across the right instruction, if you don't attend to it rightly, you won't.
[SPEAKER_03]: You won't get the right view.
[SPEAKER_01]: It seems to me there's a difference, something of a difference in what would constitute heedfulness, like you'd be heedful in regard to what for somebody without the right view, as opposed to being heedful in regard to what...
[SPEAKER_03]: So what should a person without the right view be heedful about?
[SPEAKER_01]: What I was thinking was mainly, well, heedful of the peril of not having the right view.
[SPEAKER_01]: Yeah.
[SPEAKER_03]: Or knowing that you... Heedful of the fact that you're not sought upon.
[SPEAKER_03]: And, like, take that seriously in that sense.
[SPEAKER_03]: So, if a person is heedful about it, they, you know, they won't, like, slack the effort.
[SPEAKER_03]: They won't sort of fall into the assumption that they know that which they don't, and so on, because they would constantly be hateful about the fact that, well, am I free from the first three fetters?
[SPEAKER_03]: Do I see the Four Noble Truths?
[SPEAKER_03]: Am I my own guide?
[SPEAKER_03]: Do I need to defend my views?
[SPEAKER_03]: Am I beyond doubt?
[SPEAKER_03]: All of that.
[SPEAKER_03]: It's like, no, no, no, no, no.
[SPEAKER_03]: Well, then, I'm not there yet, so I should remain hateful.
[SPEAKER_03]: So, in other words, hateful will pretty much stand for being
[SPEAKER_03]: At that stage, we'd stand... actually, at any stage, we'd stand for being honest and authentic.
[SPEAKER_03]: So, a sotāpanna, sakadāgāmī, anāgāmī should also be heedful of the fact that they still have work to do.
[SPEAKER_03]: So, it would be the same principle.
[SPEAKER_00]: It's a bit like mindfulness.
[SPEAKER_00]: You can't have too much.
[SPEAKER_03]: Exactly.
[SPEAKER_00]: Exactly.
[SPEAKER_03]: Which, I think, it's how it's sometimes translated as well, kind of synonymously.
[SPEAKER_03]: But, yeah, you can't be too heedful of the fact that, you know, you don't have the right view, or of the fact that you're not an arahant yet, and so on.
[SPEAKER_03]: That will keep you practicing and directed towards the practice.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, it seems to me that heedfulness also refers somewhat, not only to specific things you do, but like the extent to which you do them.
[SPEAKER_01]: Not only in the sense of how intensely, let's say, you practice.
[SPEAKER_01]: If you, I don't know, you could do extremely intense trying to think about things and contemplate things and be in solitude and do everything right for
[SPEAKER_01]: That constitutes just acting out of overly determined mind, which, sure, if you know what you're determining,
[SPEAKER_03]: It can be beneficial, but in and of itself, yeah, it's not... Heedfulness is on the level of, yeah, mindfulness, context, recollecting your situation, what are you still subjected to, what are the... can the non-arisen lust arise, can the non-arisen anger arise, can the non-arisen hindrances hinder you.
[SPEAKER_03]: All of that is reflected through on a kind of heedfulness.
[SPEAKER_03]: So, let me actually be careful and check these things.
[SPEAKER_03]: I might be fine now, but
[SPEAKER_03]: Do I know for sure I can...
[SPEAKER_03]: I will remain fine in the future, if circumstances change, if things change, and so on.
[SPEAKER_01]: And then, keeping that in mind, not slackening in regard to it, in the sense that, you know, you can't
[SPEAKER_01]: I think I'll just do this for a certain amount of time and then I'll take a break.
[SPEAKER_01]: It has to be basically done up to the point, up to the extent necessary, basically.
[SPEAKER_03]: Yeah, you can you can take a break from the individual determinations of I'll do this or I'll do that, if it's too much, if it's too tight.
[SPEAKER_03]: But there is never a reason to take a break from heedfulness, inasmuch there's never a reason to take a break from mindfulness.
[SPEAKER_03]: It's exactly the same.
[SPEAKER_02]: Can I take a break now?
[SPEAKER_02]: Is there a danger of me taking a break now?
[SPEAKER_03]: So, I can take a relative break, in a sense of, I mustn't forget that, yeah, there's still work to be done.
[SPEAKER_03]: So, sure, I need to catch my breath.
[SPEAKER_03]: You can't just keep going in the same pace.
[SPEAKER_03]: But that needs to be understood, that heedfulness and mindfulness, there is never a reason or a justification to take a break from.
[SPEAKER_03]: So, to that extent, you should never rest, because if your rest requires you to ignore heedfulness and mindfulness, means it's a rest of a sensual, distracting kind, for sure.
[SPEAKER_00]: It's like, eh... craving always leads to suffering.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, there's never a situation where, like, relaxing in...
[SPEAKER_03]: Unless you're completely free from it, yeah.
[SPEAKER_03]: Yeah, then...
[SPEAKER_03]: Relaxing it would mean inducing it.
[SPEAKER_03]: So, relaxing from heedfulness and mindfulness, so that, like a general sort of enduring memory of your situation, of your liabilities, of all of that, that gives rise to identification, personality view, craving, everything else.
[SPEAKER_03]: That is already there, underlying tendencies, waiting for things to become suitable for them to appear.
[SPEAKER_03]: So, mindfulness, that's why mindfulness is the path to that deathlessness, to freedom from all of it.
[SPEAKER_03]: And it's kind of learning how to be heedful and mindful without needing to do it on account of your determination and inspiration.
[SPEAKER_03]: Because then, when those things are gone, your heedfulness and mindfulness is gone, and then you're back pretty much in the perilous state of sensuality and liabilities.
[SPEAKER_03]: Because they are, if they're fully understood,
[SPEAKER_03]: But how, then, does that mindfulness, that heatheness, become effortless?
[SPEAKER_03]: By understanding it?
[SPEAKER_03]: Understanding the nature of it.
[SPEAKER_02]: And what factor is the... allows it to be effortless.
[SPEAKER_02]: So, you can understand it.
[SPEAKER_02]: Mindfulness is this, heedfulness is that, but there's that other factor which, if you see, you are automatically careful.
[SPEAKER_02]: If you develop, you automatically... Well, like yoniso manasikāra.
[SPEAKER_02]: Yeah, well, seeing the danger that you're in.
[SPEAKER_02]: Attending to it rightly.
[SPEAKER_02]: Like, you know, there are snakes in this forest.
[SPEAKER_03]: Yeah.
[SPEAKER_03]: Knowledge of that makes you heedful.
[SPEAKER_02]: Yeah, so you're always remembering.
[SPEAKER_02]: Oh, yeah, snakes.
[SPEAKER_02]: Oh, yeah, yeah.
[SPEAKER_03]: If I get bitten by a snake... Yeah, so that's why, like, again, mindfulness established correctly.
[SPEAKER_03]: Invested effort, and in that sense, like, you do need to initially make the effort to recollect the context and protect the context, but, yeah, it gives rise to knowledge, to the recognition of certain universal principles.
[SPEAKER_03]: And exactly, the dangers, how to attend to these things without losing the sight of the danger, and so on.
[SPEAKER_03]: And that is the, you know, like the famous practice of ānāpānasati.
[SPEAKER_03]: It's really not a meditation practice, it's a practice of mindfulness, which, of course,
[SPEAKER_03]: It's a meditation itself, but not the way people usually think.
[SPEAKER_03]: So, the whole idea of these types of cultivation, the satipaṭṭhānas, the ānāpānasati, is just to permeate all the aspects of your experience with the same recollectedness and same heedfulness.
[SPEAKER_03]: So, in regard to body, feeling, states of mind and thoughts.
[SPEAKER_03]: So, in other words, what I'm trying to say, even when people sometimes have this determination to practice meditation, they don't realize that ānāpānasati does not lead you to the absorptions and experience of pleasantly blissful jhāna or whatever you perceive it to be.
[SPEAKER_03]: It actually leads you to being incapable of becoming unmindful and unheedful, so to speak.
[SPEAKER_03]: So, yes, if you have a determination to practice meditation, practice the same heedfulness and mindfulness, sure,
[SPEAKER_03]: On account of knowledge of your breath, knowledge of your own sense of self, breathing like this, breathing like that, it doesn't matter.
[SPEAKER_03]: Knowledge of how you feel while you breathe, or while you are kind of walking, extending your limbs, eating, dwelling in solitude.
[SPEAKER_03]: Basically, all of these things are there as your situation, as the basis, the form, the feeling, all of that.
[SPEAKER_03]: And all you need to do is learn how to see them, discern them,
[SPEAKER_03]: So, in regard to that, there is this, let's say, subtle but kind of important distinction that you need to learn how to see them and discern them.
[SPEAKER_01]: Then, you need to be heedful in regard to them.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, there is a point where you need to kind of balance or stop trying to see and discern.
[SPEAKER_03]: And that balance would be the beginning of correct heedfulness and mindfulness.
[SPEAKER_03]: That balance would be the beginning of correct samādhi, where you're not overly concentrating and trying to do it, do it, but at the same time, you're incapable of forgetting it.
[SPEAKER_01]: Yes.
[SPEAKER_03]: So, it's effortless.
[SPEAKER_01]: And that
[SPEAKER_01]: But that point where you say, okay, this is where I just need to be heedful.
[SPEAKER_01]: Like, okay, these are the snakes in this forest, like you said.
[SPEAKER_01]: Now, that's, that is dangerous.
[SPEAKER_01]: I recognize that.
[SPEAKER_01]: So now, let me just keep being heedful in regard to that.
[SPEAKER_01]: But the mind tends to keep wanting... no, no, no, I need to keep... you know, what... how can I be sure that this is enough, basically?
[SPEAKER_01]: How can I... so...
[SPEAKER_03]: Mind tends to overdo it.
[SPEAKER_01]: Yeah.
[SPEAKER_01]: Wanting to keep doing it.
[SPEAKER_01]: Over-tighten it.
[SPEAKER_01]: Over-tighten it, overdo it.
[SPEAKER_03]: Or, dismiss the whole thing.
[SPEAKER_03]: I... or I'll run away from this forest.
[SPEAKER_03]: But that's impossible either.
[SPEAKER_03]: So, you realize, well, you...
[SPEAKER_03]: You can try to run away, which always resulted in you returning back in the forest and getting bitten by snakes, because you...
[SPEAKER_03]: Didn't discern them sufficiently enough, where the dangers are.
[SPEAKER_03]: Or, exactly, becoming overly invested in discerning even stuff that you don't really need to discern, in that sense.
[SPEAKER_03]: So, knowing where to stop, knowing... to recognize where that kind of middle ground is, that then, if you dwell on, invest in, protect, it can grow.
[SPEAKER_03]: But not if you over-tighten, or if you... if it's too loose either.
[SPEAKER_02]: Because there's that snake example, you know, walking people who would know they're snakes and then be hitting the ground constantly with a stick as you're walking through the forest and you just... but... and then when something happens, like there's danger, there's danger somewhere, you know, there's insects, there's snakes, there's this, that, there's this disease everywhere.
[SPEAKER_02]: And then, when something... was that the bat?
[SPEAKER_02]: Was that the rabies?
[SPEAKER_02]: Was that the disease that I'm waiting for?
[SPEAKER_02]: So, you just completely... it's as if you were already bitten.
[SPEAKER_02]: You don't... you've gone too far, too tight in your... you're careful, but you've lost it.
[SPEAKER_02]: You've lost the context.
[SPEAKER_02]: You've lost the plot completely.
[SPEAKER_02]: And then, if something does really bite you, you're done.
[SPEAKER_02]: So, yeah, you need to have that balance and see, okay, there is no...
[SPEAKER_02]: There's nothing here.
[SPEAKER_02]: You have a context.
[SPEAKER_02]: Yeah.
[SPEAKER_02]: There's nothing biting you, so you can... Then you can walk through the forest barefoot.
[SPEAKER_03]: To be able to basically kind of... And not freak out.
[SPEAKER_03]: ...draw a line for yourself as to how far you will allow to act out.
[SPEAKER_03]: Okay, so there are a pile of leaves here, you know, antennas might be hiding in it, so let me sweep it.
[SPEAKER_03]: But that doesn't mean now, for the rest of my time in the forest, I will walk with a broom everywhere.
[SPEAKER_03]: No, if it looks good, I avoid it.
[SPEAKER_03]: If it doesn't, it's all right.
[SPEAKER_03]: But, if you start giving in, to know, I'll sweep this, and I'll sweep that, means you started acting out of fear and concern.
[SPEAKER_03]: And then, you are losing perspective, which means, now you're even more exposed.
[SPEAKER_03]: Basically, the more you act out towards defending what you obviously, implicitly took as valuable and yours, well, the wider the basis of the danger that you're applicable to becomes.
[SPEAKER_03]: That's that monk that was in the arahant, in the suttas.
[SPEAKER_03]: Well, people didn't know he was an arahant.
[SPEAKER_03]: Going around the forest saying, oh, what a pleasure, what a joy, what a bliss.
[SPEAKER_03]: And they thought, oh, he must be remembering his former wives or something.
[SPEAKER_03]: So, they went and told the Buddha.
[SPEAKER_03]: They would have called him.
[SPEAKER_03]: He says, what do you refer to when you talk about this pleasure and the bliss?
[SPEAKER_03]: Is it previous sensuality?
[SPEAKER_03]: He's like, no, no, no, no, quite the opposite.
[SPEAKER_03]: He was a prince having five causes of sensual pleasure, but constantly fearing for his life
[SPEAKER_03]: Because he was basically, you know, in line for the throne or whatever.
[SPEAKER_03]: So, he was... he had all the guards and all the palaces, but he could never have a moment of peace, because he was just... the more he was defending himself and all the possible permutations of the danger and the attacks, the more vulnerable he was becoming internally.
[SPEAKER_02]: He was being attacked.
[SPEAKER_03]: That's already a form of fear.
[SPEAKER_03]: You're already being attacked.
[SPEAKER_03]: And then, when he abandoned
[SPEAKER_03]: The entire ownership, identity, craving became an arahant.
[SPEAKER_03]: He said, now I live in this forest with these factual dangers, tigers, elephants, snakes, yet I have no slightest concern for my life.
[SPEAKER_03]: And whenever he remembers how he used to live, he says, oh my God, what a pleasure this is now.
[SPEAKER_03]: Like immeasurable safety amidst the danger.
[SPEAKER_03]: And it starts by not acting out.
[SPEAKER_03]: It starts by not really going out of your way to
[SPEAKER_03]: To defend and address all the possible...
[SPEAKER_03]: Suffering will land on you.
[SPEAKER_03]: So, use common sense, as those other suttas say.
[SPEAKER_03]: Like, okay, well, there's clearly a raging elephant or a group of bandits or something.
[SPEAKER_03]: Okay, avoid it until you're an arahant.
[SPEAKER_03]: Then, you'll know what to do or what not to do.
[SPEAKER_03]: But that doesn't mean you kept... you're not justified to be like, well, oh, maybe this, maybe this, oh, there's bacteria here, there's this.
[SPEAKER_03]: Yeah.
[SPEAKER_03]: Yeah, there might be.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, like, the highest safety is not needing any... Protection.
[SPEAKER_01]: Protection.
[SPEAKER_03]: Yeah.
[SPEAKER_01]: But until you reach that point, it is that heedfulness that is kind of your refuge, if you discern it correctly.
[SPEAKER_01]: Like, seeing how far the... seeing the danger in, well, in things that are impermanent and things that are...
[SPEAKER_01]: Suffering in the nature of things that you would usually like to depend on, then, the only thing that you can depend on is your heedfulness, basically.
[SPEAKER_01]: Well, the thing that you that you can wholesomely depend on, that will lead you to not needing to depend on anything.
[SPEAKER_03]: Not becoming negligent.
[SPEAKER_03]: That's it.
[SPEAKER_01]: And, and the more that you dwell on... See, that's, yeah, if the one with the, with the right view, if you dwell on the nature of impermanence, nature of suffering, that it, like, naturally,
[SPEAKER_01]: The mind turns towards seeing danger in acting negligently in regard to that, or becoming... or heedless in regard to that, forgetting that.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, it's like you don't need to do anything more, or extra, or... Yeah, just within that, you need to start finding
[SPEAKER_03]: There are subtler ways that you're still not heedful enough.
[SPEAKER_03]: Yeah, exactly, because obviously... Because if, obviously, if heedfulness is seen thoroughly, developed thoroughly, you'll be an anahant.
[SPEAKER_03]: The fact that you're not, means, okay, so I'm heedful overall, but within this heedfulness, there are obviously things I still resort to heedlessly.
[SPEAKER_02]: Yes.
[SPEAKER_03]: They're not of a, you know, core, central kind and so on, but are still obstacles.
[SPEAKER_01]: That's why it's hard to do it.
[SPEAKER_01]: The thing is not to do, like, to have one particular, like, moment of insight or something, but to develop this completely, to thoroughly do it.
[SPEAKER_03]: It's not only... Yeah, to keep at it, basically.
[SPEAKER_03]: It doesn't matter.
[SPEAKER_03]: Until it's done.
[SPEAKER_03]: One insight, sixteen, just, yeah.
[SPEAKER_00]: And one way of
[SPEAKER_00]: Staying here could be to see where do I seek gratification and see the danger in those places.
[SPEAKER_03]: Yeah, definitely.
[SPEAKER_03]: Because that's why a mind would still be seeking gratification in those places.
[SPEAKER_03]: Because you haven't actually stopped and thought about, wait a minute, but that is dangerous, that pertains to the same principles I'm trying to abandon.
[SPEAKER_03]: That is not for my good, that's for my harm, that's for the harm of others, so I should better avoid it.
[SPEAKER_03]: Having considered thus, it will be easier to recognize it and then restrain yourself.